<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be answered of the sworne men in the Archdeacon of London his visitation holden the yeere. 1584. the 15. and 19. of Ianuarie.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1585</title>
            <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of London. Archdeacon (1559-1591 : Mullins)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855748</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855748</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21250</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21250)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 422:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be answered of the sworne men in the Archdeacon of London his visitation holden the yeere. 1584. the 15. and 19. of Ianuarie.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1585</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of London. Archdeacon (1559-1591 : Mullins)</author>
                  <author>Mullins, John, d. 1591.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I. W[indet] for Nicholas Ling,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date in title is old style--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:21250:1"/>
            <head>Articles to be anſwered of the Sworne men in the Archdeacon of London
his viſitation, holden the yeere. 1584. the 15. and 19. of Ianuarie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nprimis, who is your Parſon, or Vicar, and how long he hath continued with you, and whether you haue any other, which
doo ordinarily preache, reade, catechiſe or exerciſe any other function Eccleſiaſticall amongſt you, what be theyr names and
where they dwell.</p>
            <p>2. Whether your Parſon or Vicar can preache, and Whether hee haue preached his quarterly Sermons in your
Church in his owne perſon: or if any can not preache, or be not licenced themſelues, whether they haue procured their
quarter Sermons to be preached there. Item, whether beſide theſe, they haue preached or procured their monthly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
or no. And whether you haue ſuffered anie to preache, whom you haue not knowne to haue beene ſufficiently licenſed
therevnto, or hindred or forbidden any that were licenſed.</p>
            <p>3. Whether your perſon, vicar, or curate, hath obſerued in dooing diuine ſeruice and miniſtring of Sacraments, the order ſet forth by act of
Parliament, without putting in any thing of their owne or taking away, or hath omitted the Letany on ſuch dayes as it ought to be read, or els
hath omitted the wearing of the Surpleſſe in the time of their miniſtration, or no.</p>
            <p>4. Item whether your Parſons or Vicars be reſident vpon theyr benefice, and whether ſuch as are not reſident, giue the fortith part of their
benefice, béeing aboue twenty pound a yeere, to the reléefe of the poore, or no.</p>
            <p>5. Whether any doo reade, preache, or catechize with you, who doo not foure times in the yeere, at the leaſt, ſay diuine ſeruice, and miniſter the
ſacraments according to the booke of common prayer, and what be their names.</p>
            <p>6. Whether your preachers and others who be in eccleaſticall orders, doo at all times weare and vſe ſuch kinde of apparell as is preſcribed
vnto them by the booke of Aduertiſſements, and her Maieſties Iniunctions. Anno primo.</p>
            <p>7. Item whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, haue giuen notice, and warning in due time in theyr church for the due kéeping of all ſuch fiſh
daies, as are to be kept through the yéere, by the Lawes of this Realme, exhorting the people to due kéeping of them, not vpon any opinion of relgio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
or holines, but vpon their dutifull obedience to Princes, which by Gods law is due to them, procuring the welfare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Realms and countries com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to theyr charge. And alſo whether they haue the firſt ſondy of euery moneth, giuen warning openly in the Church to ſuch as be of theyr Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes,
of what eſtate ſoeuer they be, to repaire to their pariſh Church in ſuch ſort as by the Lawes of this Realme is appointed, vppon paine to be
preſented for the ſame or no.</p>
            <p>8. Whether your Curate doo ſerue in your Church not licenſed and allowed by the Byſhop, or other ordinarie, vnder his ſeale, or hand at the
leaſt, or béeing beneficed els where, doo ſerue with you as a Curat, or no.</p>
            <p>9. Whether any Farmer of any benefice, take vpon him to admit or reiect any miniſter, to ſerue or not ſerue where he is Farmer, without the
aucthoritie of the Ordinarie, or no.</p>
            <p>10. Item, whether ſince the laſt viſitation, your pariſh Clarke, or any other, not béeing miniſter, or Deacon, or not being licenſed by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie,
haue taken: vpon them to beginne or ſay ſeruice, or miniſter any Sacraments, or diſtribute the Lords cuppe, or reade the Homely in your
Pariſh &amp; what be theyr names.</p>
            <p>11. Item what perſons you haue in your pariſh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doo teach &amp; inſtruct children, and what be the ſayed ſcholemaſters names, whether they teach
publikely or priuately in any mans houſe, &amp; whether ſuch Schoolemaiſters as doo teach the Latine tongue in your pariſh, doo reade vnto their Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
twice euery wéeke at the leaſt, an ordinary Lecture out of the Latine Catechiſme, lately ſet foorth, and allowed by publique authoritie: And
whether ſuch as teache youth to reade Engliſh, doo bring vp their children in reading this Catechiſme in Engliſh, and of other Bookes agréeable to
the Quéenes procéedinges. And whether they behaue themſelues honeſtly, and both repaire to Church orderly themſelues and ſo much as lyeth in
them, procure that theyr ſcholers alſo frequent the ſame.</p>
            <p>12. Item whether you doo knowe, beléeue, or haue heard ſay, that your Parſon, Vicar or Curate, doth ſue any of his pariſhioners, or any other
perſon before any lay Iudge, contrary to the Eccleſiaſticall Lawes of his Realme, and the Statute made 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. for any cauſe of thithes, or other
Eccleſiaſtical duties.</p>
            <p>13. Item whether ſuch ground as in your Chanſel or Church is broken vp for burials, or otherwiſe, be decently made vp againe, and if it be
not, by whoſe fault it lyeth vnmade vp.</p>
            <p>14. Whether your Churchwardens doo duely account once in the yéers before the Parſon, Vicar or Curate, and the Pariſhioners, for all ſuch
Church goodes and ſtokes of money therevnto belonging, as hath cone to theyr handes in the time of theyr office, or no.</p>
            <p>15. Item, whether you haue a comely Communion table, with furniture there vnto belonging, that is to know, a comely ioyned Table, a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely
Carpet thereto, being no hearſe cloth or pall for burials, a comfy table cloth, with two handſome Communion Cuppes, and a de<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t patent
of ſiluer, to miniſter the Lords bread vpon, and alſo two comely pots of Pewter to fetch wine to ſerue for the Lordes Table, reſerued &amp; kept cleane
to that vſe onely, being no Tauerne pots, or no.</p>
            <p>16 Whether there be any in your Pariſh, that doth openly, courtely, or guilefully, by any ſleight or colour, detaine any tithe or duety due to
your Parſon, Vicar, Clearke, or any other Eccleſiaſticall officer, or no.</p>
            <p>17 Item whether the bread and wine for the communions all the yéere be prouided by the Curate and Church<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the charges of the
pariſh according to the booke of common prayer and whether the ſame be truly collected of the pariſhioners and be beſtowed according to the ſame
vſe of bread and wine onely, or no.</p>
            <p>18. Item whither anie pariſhioners taxed or rated to paye towardes the ſaide bread or wine at the ſayde Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munions doe att anie time refuge
to paye their portions once a yéere vnto the Churchwardens or ther deputyes when yt is demaunded, or no.</p>
            <p>19. Whether your Churchwardens doo collect and gather at euery Communion, the offering of the communicants and after the Communion
doo put the ſame in the poore mennes cheſt as it is appointed by the boke of common prayer. and whether the ſayd collection, or any part thereof, be
imployed to any other vſe, then to the reléefe of the poore, and what the ſame vſe is.</p>
            <p>20. Whether there be any y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doo let or diſturbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Miniſter, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of reading the diuine ſeruice, or the preacher while he is in the pulpet, or no.</p>
            <p>21. Whether there be any in your Pariſh that either obſtinatlye refuge or by negligence doo not frequent in holy dayes &amp; Sondayes your pariſh
Church, to heare diuine ſeruice, or hath not, being of lawfull age &amp; hauing no other lawfull impediment receaued the Holy Communion thrice this
yéere, and what be theyr names.</p>
            <p>22. Item you ſhall preſent ſo néere as you can learne howe the children of ſuch as refuſe to come to Church, are brought vp, vnder what Schole
maiſter or Tutor, where and in what ſchoole. And alſo you ſhal diligently enquire of all recuſant or not recuſant, as haue any of their children beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de
the ſeas, and preſent who they be, and where their ſayd children remaine as far as you know, beléeue or haue heard ſay.</p>
            <p>23. And whether any perſons being excommunicated, and not reconciled, or yong folke that can not ſay the Catechiſme, or elderly folke that
cannot ſay the Lordes prayer, the beléefe, and the ten commandements in the Engliſh tongue, or being ſtayned with any notorious vice, haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed
to receiue the holy Communion, and haue béene admitted therevnto, or no.</p>
            <p>24. Item, whether there hath or dooth any ſtranger ſoiorne at any Inne, or other houſe in your Pariſh, at or about Eaſter, and hath continued
there any long ſeaſon at other times of the yéere, &amp; hath not reſorted to your church, &amp; communicated there, who they be and what be theyr names.</p>
            <p>25. Whether anie of your Pariſh hath detained theyr child or children from Baptiſme in theyr owne Pariſh church, or haue carryed the ſame
to be baptized in any other place, who they be, and what be theyr names.</p>
            <p>26. Whether there be any bankets or common drinkings, enterludes, or playes kept in your Church or Chapell or no.</p>
            <p>27. Whether any Artificer hath or doth follow theyr worke or ſcience, or handicraft on the ſunday, as Goldſmith, Tayler, Clothworker or ſuch
like And whether they or any other Artificer doo ſo occupy themſelues, theyr ſeruants or apprentices, on that day or no.</p>
            <p>28. Item whether there be any man or woman in your Pariſh, that ſuppreſſeth &amp; fulfilleth not the laſt will and teſtament of the dead, or defea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth
the children or other of theyr legacies or portions: or if any executor or executrix, adminiſtrator or adminiſtrators, do vniuſtly withhold any
gift, or be queſt made to any poore or impotent perſons to hoſpitalles and poore priſoners, either of this Citie or els where, to poore ſcholers, maydens
marriages, the mending of the high waies and bridges, or to any good and godly vſe and purpoſe or no.</p>
            <p>29. Item whether there be any in your Pariſh infected with any notorious vice, as whoredome open or ſecret maintainers thereof, or any that
doth hanntany ſuſpected houſes, any perſons married within the degrees of conſanguinitie or affinitie forbidden, or any perſon béeing lawfully mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
that liues ſlaunderouſly a ſunder or any that were maryed without banes three times orderlie aſked, hauing no lawfull dipenſation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
or hath married againe, theyr olde wiues or huſbandes being yet aliue ſhewing both the names of them that ſo were married, and the mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter
that ſo marryed them: any adulterers, ſwearers, drunkards, ſlaunderers of theyr neighbors, or any other like vice, or no.</p>
            <p>30. Item, whether any doo vſe any conuenticles or meetings, handling or expounding of ſcriptures in any priuat houſe or place, other then in
the common Church, who they be, where and when they own.</p>
            <p>31. Item, whether you doo know, that within your pariſh there is (or are) any perſon or perſons notoriouſly knowne or ſuſpected by probable
tokens or common fame, to be an vſurer, or doth offend by any colour or meanes directly or indirectly in the ſame, if any ſuch he, that you and euery
of you, by vertue of your othe preſent the name or names of ſuch offender or offenders.</p>
            <p>32. Item whether your Byble or ſeruice bookes to doo you common ſeruice on be whole, not torne rente, nor blinde, and whether the ſame
be of that tranſlation which is authoriſed by conſent of the Biſhops of this Realme or no.</p>
            <p>33. Item, whether you haue afitte booke of paper, to write in all chriſtnings, burials, and weddings, doone in your Pariſh: whether your parſon
Vicar, or Curat, doo diligentlie note in that Booke once in the wéeke, the ſaid chriſtnings, burials, and weddings, in the preſence of the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens
or of one of them: and whether the ſayd booke be ſafelie kept vnder lockes and keyes: whether the Parſon, Vicar, or Curat hath one, and the
Churchwardens another or no.</p>
            <p>34. Item whether any houſholder in your pariſh do ſuffer any plaies or games in his houſe or yard or let any people in, to the ende to ſée any
ſuch playes or games, on any ſunday or holy day before euening prayer be cleane doone in that Pariſh, who they be and what be their names.</p>
            <p>35. Ithem whether you know any matter Eccleſiaſticall woorthye of redreſſe in your Pariſh beſide theſe that are ſet downe before, or no.</p>
            <p>You are to bring your anſwere to all theſe Articles into Maſter Gods office on the 12. February 1584. alſo the 15. of March next, the 15. of Iune, and the 15. of September following
becauſe reformation may be bad of ſuch offences as ſhalbe by you preſented for many eſcape vnpreſented, becauſe you preſent but once a yeere.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>I, W.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Ling.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
